<chapter xml:id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>

<note>Right now this is not an introduction, but a random collection of topics that does not fit yet in the current document structure.
Sorry for that!</note>

		<section xml:id='macrossub'><title>Defining and Using Macros</title>

		<para>Macros control the execution of RePros, other Macros, and shell scripts.
		Several RePros with specified parameter settings can be 
		executed one after the other by combining them in a macro.
		Macros can be easily customized.
		Read <xref linkend='macros' endterm='macrostitle'/> for more on this topic.</para>
		</section>


		<section xml:id='datafiles'><title>Recorded Data</title>

		<para>Whenever a recording is started, a new directory is created
		in which all recorded data are stored.
		The directories are named yyyy-mm-dd-aa, where yyyy is the year,
		mm the month, dd the day, and aa is aa, ab, ac ... az, ba, bb, ...</para>

		<para>RELACS itself creates the following files:</para>

		<para><itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>traces.sw?</emphasis>: The raw data from the data acquisition board.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>*-events.dat</emphasis>: Text files with the events.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>trigger.dat</emphasis>: Text file with information of each stimulus
		  and indices into the traces.sw? and *-events.dat files.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>repros.dat</emphasis>: The executed repros.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>info.dat</emphasis>: The data from the meta-data dialog.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist></para>

		<para>Each RePro may write its own files.
		Those files are usually used for further data analysis.
		See the documentation of the RePro for further information
		(<guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem> in the RePro's submenu).</para>
		</section>

		<section xml:id='relacsconfig'><title>RELACS configuration files</title>
		<para>There a two configuration files:</para>

		<para><itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>relacs.cfg</emphasis>: Basic configuration of RELACS.
		Setup of the  data acquisition (channels, sampling rate, etc.),
		filters, event detectors, attenuators, manipulators, and other devices.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>relacsplugins.cfg</emphasis>: In this configuration file the options of all plugins including RePros are stored.
		The first section defines the meta-data dialog.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist></para>

		</section>
		
<section xml:id='pluginconcept'><title xml:id='pluginconcepttitle'>RELACS Plugins</title>
<para>
RELACS plugins are C++ classes compiled as shared libraries
which are automatically loaded into the RELACS program during startup.
They can be compiled independently of the RELACS program
and reloaded into the running RELACS program.
All parts of RELACS which code something specific for a setup are plugins:
<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>RePro</emphasis>(Research Program): Analyses the acquired data, generates
		and puts stimuli out.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Filter</emphasis>: Filters or detects events (e.g. spikes) in the acquired data.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Control</emphasis>: Control some hardware, analyze data independently and in parallel to the RePros,
		or provides some usefull general information about the recording.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Model</emphasis>: Simulate data.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>AnalogInput</emphasis>: Communication with a data acquisition driver for reading analog data.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>AnalogOutput</emphasis>: Communication with a data acquisition driver for writing analog data.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Attenuate</emphasis>: Sets the right attenuation level for a requested output intensity.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Attenuator</emphasis>: Sets the attenuation level of an attenuator device.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Device</emphasis>: Any other device.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>

</section>

</chapter>